Early in the 20th year of Yuankang
원강 20년 초
Zu Kun broke through Beiyu Pass
조곤은 북역관을 함락하고
Afterward
오노와
With the Wuzhao at the Hanshui line
한수 일대에서
In a long stalemate
장시간 대치에 들어갑니다
In June of the 23rd year of Yuankang
원강 23년 6월
Zu Kun again petitioned for the northern expedition
조곤이 다시금 북벌을 주청 올렸으나
The emperor did not approve
천자는 불허하면서
Ordered him to withdraw and return to court
병사를 이끌고 철수할 것을 명합니다
Rise, rise
일어나게 일어나
Yet the northern people knelt to keep the royal army
북지 백성들은 무릎 꿇고 선나라군을 만류했으며
Volunteer armies also responded
의병들도 이에 호응합니다
That September
같은 해 9월
Zu Kun captured Zhongzhou
조곤이 중주를 공략하여
Causing great shock in the court
조정이 크게 놀랍니다
Defeat would harm the state
지면 나라가 망합니다
Your Majesty
폐하
This war really cannot continue
더는 싸우면 안 됩니다
The court issued eight imperial edicts
조정에선 교지 8개를 내려
Ordering Zu Kun not to advance further
조곤의 진군을 막고
While cutting off his supplies
군량미와 마초를 끊었으며
Secretly ordered Chen Ying and others to withdraw
진응 군에는 철수하라는 밀령을 내립니다
October
10월
Chen Ying
진응은
Crossed south over Tianhe
남하해서 천하를 건너
Occupied the ferry behind Zu Kun
조곤의 후방 부두를 불법으로 점거합니다
Zu Kun knew
조곤은 단숨에
To press on
영안성까지
To take Yong'an was hopeless
쳐들어갈 수 없음을 깨닫고
Years of war's accumulated ills
그동안 전쟁에서 쌓인 적폐와
Coupled with inner frustration
마음속 울분으로 인해
Illness struck like a mountain
병세가 악화되면서
General
장군
Soon
얼마 안 되어
Soon passed away at
북역관에서
Beiyu Pass
세상 뜨고 맙니다
General
장군
My father told me
아버지는 젊은 시절을
He lived in Yong'an as a youth
영안에서 보냈으나
Always thought Yong'an wasn't special
영안을 좋아하지 않았어요
Those scholars' Ba willow trees
서생들이 말하는
Yong'an flowers
강가의 버드나무도
Were just ordinary
영안의 꽃도
All these years
별 볼 일 없대요
I never thought my father
난 고향에 대한 애착을
Cared much about that hometown
아버지한테서 못 느꼈어요
Doing all this
아버지가 한 모든 건
Was just for advancement
앞날과 명성을
For reputation
위해서이고
For those tens of thousands of
수하의 수만 군사들
Hungry mouths under him
생계 때문이라 생각했거든요
But this time
하지만 이번에
Taking Beiyu Pass
북역관을 함락하고 나서
I realized
아버지 마음을
He actually cared so much
알았어요
He stood right here
아버지는 여기에 서서
He told me
이렇게 높은 곳에 올랐는데
Standing this high
왜 영안이
Why still can't see Yong'an?
안 보이냐고 묻더군요
Raising my eyes, I see the sun
해는 고개 들면 보이는데
But not Yong'an
영안은 안 보이네
Maybe when people get old
사람이 늙으면
They always miss home
고향이 더 그리운가 봐요
Your Highness in the palace, honored and precious
황성에서 존귀하고 호화로운
Servants like clouds
삶을 사시는 전하께서
Pushing for the northern expedition
북벌을 고집하시는 건
Do you truly care about these northern lives
정말 북쪽의 비천한 백성들을 위해서인가요?
Or to win hearts
민심을 얻어 황위 쟁탈에
To gain leverage in the succession?
유리하기 위해서인가요?